Guide to the Willard Dryden Paddock Photographs and Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Willard Dryden Paddock photographs and papers
1912-1988
1912-1941
YCAL MSS 848
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(3 boxes)
Collection of photographs and papers, chiefly from 1912 to 1941, which document the work of American artist Willard Dryden Paddock and his activities with his wife Charlotte Elizabeth Smith Paddock, as well as related material collected and created by his nieces Mary Steichen Calderone and Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen from 1954 to 1988.
Paddock, Willard Dryden, 1873-1956
Paddock, Charlotte Elizabeth Smith, 1874-1936
Steichen, Charlotte Rodina, 1908-1988
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Francesca Calderone-Steichen, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 3 (photographic negatives): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Edward Steichen, Photograph Albums of the Steichen Family (YCAL MSS 593). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Willard Dryden Paddock (1873-1956)
Willard Dryden Paddock was an American artist. He was born in Brooklyn, New York, the son of John D. Paddock (born 1842) and Elizabeth C. Adams Paddock (born 1849). In 1893, Paddock began training with sculptor Herbert Adams (1858-1945) at the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn. In 1895, he earned a two-year scholarship to study in Europe, which included periods at the Académie Colarossi and Académie Julian in Paris.
In 1922, Paddock became an associate member of the National Academy of Design, and the following year he co-founded the Kent Art Association in Kent, Connecticut. Beginning in 1927, he was a member of the faculty at Pratt Institute.
His sculptural work ranged from small whimsical pieces and busts, usually for the Gorham Manufacturing Company in Providence, Rhode Island, to fountains and monumental structures. Paddock is known for his memorials to World War I, which include the War Memorial in Stratford, Connecticut, and a flagpole on the Pratt Institute campus. His other significant works include the Noah Webster Memorial Fountain for Amherst College in Amherst, Massachusetts, and the Alfred Nobel Memorial at the United Engineering Societies Building in New York City. Paddock also produced a number of paintings.
In 1902, Paddock married Charlotte Elizabeth Smith Paddock (1874-1936), the daughter of John Randolph Smith (1836-1917) and Frances R. Keet Smith (1844-1939). Her younger sister was Clara Emma Smith Steichen (1875-1952), who was married to Edward Jean Steichen (1879-1973) from 1903 until their divorce in 1922. Around 1912, the Paddocks moved to a small farm at 28 Spooner Hill Road in South Kent, Connecticut, where he also maintained a studio. Their nieces Mary Steichen Calderone (1904-1998) and Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen (1908-1988) would often visit the farm. After the death of his wife, Paddock returned to New York City, where he lived until his death.
Scope and Contents
Collection of photographs and papers, chiefly from 1912 to 1941, which document the work of American artist Willard Dryden Paddock and his activities with his wife Charlotte Elizabeth Smith Paddock, as well as related material collected and created by his nieces Mary Steichen Calderone and Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen from 1954 to 1988.
Photographic material in the collection includes a photograph album created by Charlotte Paddock and Kate Steichen that documents activities on a small farm owned by the Paddocks in South Kent, Connecticut, 1912-1936. Other photographs in the collection document sculptures created by Paddock, with many depictions of Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918), an outdoor sculpture and functional sundial that depicts a boy sitting cross-legged with an open scroll in his lap and holding a twig with a spider affixed to the wire that acts as the gnomon.
A small quantity of papers in the collection document some of his sculptures and paintings, including an illustrated catalog of sculptures, as well as programs for exhibitions and dedications, circa 1929-1941. Other papers, 1978-1988, document his nieces' interests in his artwork and the home in South Kent, Connecticut.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Photographs, 1912-1978. II. Papers, 1929-1988.
Sculptors; Sculpture -- Pictorial works; Sundials -- Pictorial works; Connecticut -- Pictorial works; South Kent (Conn.) -- Pictorial works; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Sculptors -- Connecticut -- 20th Century; Calderone, Mary Steichen, 1904-1998; Paddock family -- Pictorial works; Paddock, Charlotte Elizabeth Smith, 1874-1936; Paddock, Willard Dryden, 1873-1956; Steichen family -- Pictorial works; Steichen, Charlotte Rodina, 1908-1988
- Photographs, 1912-1978; Series I; 1 volume and 40 folders
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Photograph Album, Photographic Prints, and Photographic Negatives
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 3 (photographic negatives): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains photographic material that visually documents the Paddock farm, home, and studio in South Kent, Connecticut, as well as Paddock's sculptures.
  - Photograph Album, 1912-1966; 1 album (134 photographic prints) (Box 1)
    Photograph album with images related to a small farm owned by Willard Dryden Paddock and Charlotte Smith Paddock at 28 Spooner Hill Road, South Kent, Connecticut, 1912 to 1936, with the bulk from 1930 to 1936.
    Charlotte Smith Paddock compiled the first portion of the album, circa 1930-1936, and her niece, Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen, compiled the second portion, circa 1966, using photographs from her aunt's collection. The second portion includes copious manuscript captions transcribed by Steichen from inscriptions made by Paddock on the versos of the photographic prints, as well as descriptions authored by Steichen.
    Informal portraits of individuals include Charlotte Paddock, Willard Dryden Paddock, Clara Smith Steichen and Kate Steichen. The album also includes portraits of Kate Steichen with Ray Bolton, and a portrait of her with Carol Silverberg. Other identified individuals include psychoanalyst Adam Empie and his wife, author Margery Hazzard Wells Empie, as well as a portrait of actor Walter Hampden.
    Images depict interiors and exteriors of the home, as well as views of gardens and surrounding farmland, and a cottage on the property. A couple of images depict sculpture created by Paddock, including Rose in the Wind and a small sculpture of a pig.
    Images of activities related to farm life include plowing fields and gathering hay, as well as cooking in an open-hearth fireplace. Images of animals on the farm include cows, dogs, geese, horses, oxen, pigs, and rabbits.
    A group of detail photographs, probably created for an unrealized book about fires and fireplaces by Willard Dryden Paddock, include images of fireplace implements, including andirons, grates, and tongs, as well as cooking tools.
    A group of images document the first automobiles owned by Kate Steichen, including a Ford Model T in 1926 and a Ford Model A in 1930.
    A printed poem, "The Little House," by Edith D. Osborne, is pasted to the front endpaper of the album. A formerly laid-in note by Kate Steichen describes a picnic table on the property modelled after Stonehenge.
    Images not created on the property include canoeing on the Housatonic River in western Connecticut and an exterior portrait made in 1912 of Charlotte Smith Paddock with the family dog at their home at 82 Grove Street on Sheridan Square in New York City.
  - Photographic Prints
    - Photographs of the sculpture Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918) in the studio of Willard Dryden Paddock, 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Exterior photographs of the sculpture Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918), 1920 July 16; 6 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Accompanied with notes, probably by Willard Dryden Paddock, about different photographic exposures
    - Exterior photograph of the sculpture Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918) in the Rose Garden of "Killenworth," a mansion owned by George Dupont Pratt in Glen Cove, New York, circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Exterior photographs of the sculpture Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918), circa 1920; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Studio photograph of the sculpture Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918), circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Interior photograph of the living and dining room in the Paddock house at South Kent, Connecticut, circa 1920; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Studio photographs of Portrait of a Young Girl (1919?-1922?) with exposure notes, 8 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 7)
      The sculpture depicts Mary Steichen Calderone as a child
      Related Archival Materials note
      Associated materials: See also: Photographic negatives, Box 3, folders 28-37
    - Interior photograph of Rodina (1926?), circa 1926 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      The sculpture depicts Kate Steichen
    - Ira W. Martin, Photographic postcards of the World War Memorial Flagstaff (1926) at the Pratt Institute, Brooklyn, New York, published by the Santway Photo-Craft Company, Watertown, New York, circa 1934; 2 photomechanical postcards (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Flagstaff designed by John Mead Howells with sculptural elements by Paddock
    - Exterior photograph of Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen posed sitting beside the War Memorial at the West Broad Street Green in Stratford, Connecticut, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Steichen modeled for the sculpture
    - Interior color photograph of Rodina (1926?), circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Color photograph of the sculpture Flight (1925), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographic Negatives, 17 photographic negatives
    - Exterior photographs of the sculpture Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918) mounted on a rock, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
    - Exterior photographs of the sculpture Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918) mounted on a pedestal, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - Studio photographs of Portrait of a Young Girl (1919?-1922?) (Box 3, Folder 29-38)
    - Exterior photograph of the Paddock home and studio in South Kent, Connecticut, circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Studio photographs of Rose in the Wind (1927?), circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
- Papers, circa 1929-1988; Series II; 12
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series II includes papers, circa 1929-1941, chiefly related to sculptures and other artwork by Paddock, including a privately printed catalog illustrated with examples of his sculptural work. The series also includes later correspondence and other documentation, 1978-1988, related to his artwork and the farm in South Kent, Connecticut.
  - F. Denks, Inc. Announcement for the Permanent Exhibition of Sculpture for the House and Garden by Willard Paddock, circa 1929 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Some Reproductions of Works by Willard Paddock (New York: Privately printed ), 1928 April (Box 2, Folder 14)
    2 catalogs
    Limited edition of one thousand copies. These copies numbered 1 and 252.
  - Denks Galleries. Program for an exhibition of paintings by Willard Paddock, 1929 April 3-30 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Stratford, Connecticut. Program for the dedication of the War Memorial at the West Broad Street Green in Stratford, Connecticut, 1931 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Accompanied by newspaper clippings describing the event and a humorous editorial about it by George S. Smith
  - Gould, Ralph Edgar, United States National Bureau of Standards. Sundials. Circular of the National Bureau of Standards, no. 402. (Washington: United States Government Printing Office), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Card from National Art Week in New York City for the sculpture Flight (1925), 1941 November 17-23 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence between Robert S. Ratner and the Brooklyn Museum, 1978 December 20-1979 August 21 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Ratner, an attorney working on behalf of Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen, relays her offer to purchase of a bust depicting Mary Steichen Calderone from the museum
  - Correspondence between Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen and Emily Hopson, president of the Kent Historical Society, 1983 July 19, August 28 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    A single exchange of letters regarding the historical society and Steichen seeking copies of a catalog of works by Paddock
  - Correspondence between Charlotte "Kate" Rodina Steichen and Mary Steichen Calderone, 1987 May 27, August 20 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    A single exchange of letters about works by Paddock owned by the family, and Calderone giving her copy of Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918) to Steichen
  - J. M. Layton & Co., Insurance binder for Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918), 1987 September 2 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Burt Chernow, Appraisal of sculptures Sundial, Boy With Spider (1916-1918) and Flight (1925), 1987 September 19 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Accompanied by notes by Kate Steichen
  - Photocopy of a letter from Mary Steichen Calderone to Deborah L. Chabrian, 1988 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Chabrian had recently purchased the former Paddock home and studio in South Kent, Connecticut